[Music]
Hello
everybody. Um we will talk here about
uh modular monoliths and ddding
principles. What you have to not expect
from this talk is all the theory in
particular all the theory about theDD
because we want to just see the code and
how we implemented an example uh based
on how we use uh
modular monoliths and uh the library
that we chose to
implement. Where are we?
Hi everyone. I Matia Curio and it's my
first time here at the Spring IO as a
speaker. So I'm a little bit excited for
that. Um I'm a Google certified
architect and uh an enterprise architect
in Adesso and I basically love well
written code. I love quality and I have
been a spring software developer for
more than 10 years and
okay
I'm Gregorio I work in Adesso too uh in
the Italian branch I'm an enterprise
architect too I'm a Google developer
expert on the uh cloud platform um in
particular for everyone or everything
that concern the uh modern enterprise
architecture
and I lead the GDG Pascara in my town.
Okay, let's start about something that
will introduce the uh the code that I
promised you at the start. So, let's
talk about microservices. Let's
understand what is good about
microservices and what is not really
really good about
microservices. Okay, first of all, we
have autonomy. Every micros service has
his own
autonomy. We have a lot of
scalability. A single micros service can
scale horizontally because you know it's
just small micro and you can start to
replicate it.
resilience. It should be uh in a good
design it should be resilient a single
micros service but we also have a
complex orchestration
needed in a cluster maybe okay we use
kubernetes maybe it's still complex no
matter how you put it it's still an
orchestration that is needed to you know
make everything work and work
together we can have network failures
It happens. Imagine just a distributed
cluster and you know you have to have
replicas and fall tolerance and so
on and we have a tight coupling via sync
calls and that's something that we
should try to uh address uh every
time also distributed transaction and
the observability puts some overhead to
microservices.
this the
other the upside of the the coin
monoliths. So we are using microservices
because we started from
monoliths. So if we we are using
microservices maybe we understood at a
certain time point that monoliths were
not good or really good. So why we we
chose to start using microservices?
What's what were the good things and
what was the not so good things about
monoliths? Well, they're simple. We can
debug them easy because you know you
have the the whole application in just
one
application. But still they are tight
coupled.
It's not
clear the the ownership. It's not clear
because you know you have everything in
just one place. So the code starts
to it could be okay and clear. It could
not be it's not inside the design uh how
or who has the ownership of something.
and we have fragile
interdependencies among every single
part of a single
monolith. Okay, so we've seen that both
the approaches has some good things and
some a little less good
things. what we are trying to uh do with
the code that we'll show you. We are
trying to take both sides and take the
good things, good parts of both sides
using a modular
monolith. Oops. So maybe we can take the
best of the two worlds microservices and
monoliths and create something that has
internal internal modules with strong
boundaries. So we don't have tight
coupling anymore because we have a
boundary. We want to try to create
something that should be maintainable,
testable,
understandable and not not also that we
want to achieve that with a maintainable
testable and understandable architecture
and it should be documented and that's
something that we can ensure with the
tools that will uh use
NC whenever we need with a modular
monolith we can choose to take it and
evolve to
microservices. You know when the project
starts when the application starts to
grow it still lacks something. It still
becomes complex and we
will from time to time need to switch to
microservices. So they're not evil. They
just have some pitfalls and we need to
understand them and we need to to choose
the be the best architecture the best
tools for our
need. Okay. What we used to uh create
our modular monoliths we uses spring
model and the spring model by
documentation allows the de developers
to build well structured spring boot
application. what I want to
um you can read the the documentation
for everything but what I want to
um let you um see here is this part
because the modules should be driven by
the
domain. Okay. So we want an application.
We want to create
modules. Let's say we imagine an
application for this conference. So
let's say the single session and the
attendee the single session should be a
module. Maybe the attendee should be
another module. Maybe I don't
know what's the driver. What drives me
to decide what's inside a single module
and what's should be outside the single
model? Well, spring model spring model
it says that the modules should be
driven by the domain. What does it mean?
Okay, driven by the domain should let us
think about domain driven development
theory not included but we will have
modeling bounded
context we will enforce boundaries in
our code and that's something very
interesting because you know it's not
just I decide to have
boundaries it's not just that I will
enforce boundaries
is and we can leverage events for both
intramodules and interm modules
communication. That's something that
will um help us when we want to evolve
as a singular modular monolith to
microservices because you know
everything every communication is
already done with the
events. For the DDD part, we chose J
molecules. It's a library that uh help
us to work with
DDD. We will see it in the code. And
just
for just to start uh I talked about code
code. Okay, let's see the code. First of
all, this is our application. So, as you
can see, it's still loading
because we are starting
from almost a scratch.
Okay, the first thing that I want you to
see is the pom xml because we have the
dependency from modulate and the
dependency from J
molecules ddd and
events. In reality, we also have layered
architecture because we will see that
our architecture we we chose an
architecture. We chose a layered
architecture and we enforce it. So we
test it, we enforce it, we document it
using something that J molecules give us
together with uh modulate.
Okay. What's inside this project? That's
for now. We have just an application and
we have a session that should be our
first
module. What's the entity? We just want
to handle a
session. And this is an entity just a
simple entity. We have a repository
easy. We have a
service and also we have a controller a
very basic controller.
Okay. What we want to see right now
first of all you can see that uh let's
get back to here. You can see that this
entity is not uh a ddd entity. It's just
a Jakarta persistence entity. So it's
just some something that maps the entity
to the database. We are not using
DDD but we should use so we chose to
create a module. We chose to maybe put
this session in a single module but we
are not enforcing DDD yet. Spring module
it suggest to use
DDD. So why
not write a test that can ensure us that
everything that we put inside our
application respects some boundaries and
some rules that we decide. So we design
an an architecture. We describe it in a
single
test. And to do this we
have as you can see archunit and j
molecules that help help us to describe
the architecture that we want and the
single test should just say okay you are
not using
the so it should
fail. Okay, as you can see, just one of
these tests is okay, but the other ones
are
all failing. So, elements should be
incorrect layers. We are not putting
them in correct layers. And for bounded
context isolation, for example. So, we
wrote a a series of uh checks that we
are not
yet implementing. So let's switch to
another revision. So let's start working
on our
code and let's say that our session
module
and
boundary change to first of all
infrastructure persistence and you can
see the session entity is here because
we have something totally different. we
are starting to um design it in a DDD
way. So we have an infrastructure, we
have a domain, we have the session here.
So the aggregate root of the
DDD, we have the
identity intended in the way of
DDD. We also have for example this price
that is used here. But as you can see,
it's
not inside the session entity. And
oops. No, it's inside. Okay. Uh but but
but okay, we also have the application
and presentation API. The session
controller is moved in the presentation
API.
this kind of
um architecture so application config
domain infrastructure and so on is
everything that we put inside these
tests. So we are checking that
everything that we write inside our
application respect that kind of
architecture. Let's find out if the code
is okay right now.
Okay, everything is
green. Why this is important? We wrote
some rules that checks the way we are
writing our code. So the the
architecture of our application and
basically we are saying that our tests
ensure that we are
writing the code in the way that we
designed it. That's something that is
self-documenting because you know when a
new developer uh join this project this
application where do I put the entity?
Okay, whenever you want just try
out when you execute this test if you
put it in the wrong place it will say it
that you done it wrong and that's
something very powerful. So it's
self-documented and help helps us a lot
to understand how to uh go on writing
code. Okay, Matia, I leave it to you for
the next layers. Thanks.
And yes, so basically we are saying that
we are able to enforce some way or to
guide to provide guidelines that are
written in our code with tests that we
can um use in order to test our further
developments and also in order to teach
how people can read the same can can
write the same code. Okay. in the same
way and we can test it for
example using a use case that we
have
yeah not not here in the application we
have a fine session that is a use
case and if I put here for example a
dependencies for a service that not J
molecule service but it is spring
service and I run the test
Again it should say that there is a
problem and the problem is that I should
avoid to using spring services in my
application layer and we can a little
bit more in detail see how is it
enforced. Basically, we have this
package info java that has this
application layer um application layer
annotation use it to write our tests. So
when we find that in the fine session
class there is an annotation and this
annotation is non not compliant with our
structure with our defined structure we
raise an error and again we can move on
we can move
on showing one interesting thing this is
from JPA so we implemented the mapper
basically
that
translate automatically without writing
any code our session to our session
entity and here we have how we have the
persistence concerns. So how
this value objects or identifier that
are all invariance for example
title for example also
speakers is used by our code and we can
also run it and
hopefully it will work too.
Okay. And now we have the session today
with all the speaks the speech and the
speakers are of course anonymized
because of privacy you know but we have
also price and we can search. So we
implemented a lot yeah a little bit
things interesting for example
crafting. Yeah, this is the conference
we are attending now and we can also of
course create
something
more. For
example, the ch the change
price. Yeah, it was supposed to be a lot
a little bit more live coding, but we
have a a lot to show.
So we will move like that. So we now
implemented another use case for the
session that is change
price. And here we have always the same
structure. We have this use case that
does this change price and use the sess
a session
repository that is a repository a J
molecules repository. So a repository
intended by DDD and we have all the
defined uh interfaces for our repository
and this repository only return our
aggregate our root aggregate. Our root
aggregate uh
is uh who defines the boundaries of our
transactions. Basically it is it
responsible to grant that all the
changes happens
there and when we implement this change
price we basic we we basically have this
method execute we find a session by ID
and we use the method that is inside our
aggregate root change price and all the
controls about the the validity of the
operation that we are doing on the
aggregate should happen here. So if you
pass a price that that is null. So yeah
probably you have to define uh a more uh
descriptive exception but the price
basically is a value object that is auto
validating. So if you have a price that
is not null this price is also greater
or equal or or equals zero. And this is
oops this is really really um powerful
because you can just trust that the
objects that you are passing the
instances that you are passing to your
aggregate if they are not null they are
valid and this is granted
by the value object
itself and
again yeah Coming back to the change
price. Yeah, probably in the session we
have also this register
event that basically says that the price
is changed. The price is changed and
it's a register. So what happens when
the JPA persists the entity related to
this
aggregate? It is responsibility. This is
the magic code of modulate and spring.
It is granted that you will have an
event published as soon as the
transaction commits. This grants you the
transactional outbox pattern out of the
box. That is something that is really
really important when you have to
leverage both
on persistence and events and external
events because you have at some stage at
least to have the eventual
consistency and we can see also another
interesting thing here we are have
defined
more or less we have several kind of
event listener that we can
have this is the basic one. This is an
event listener that is transactional. So
it is synchronous and transactional. So
if you run your code in a
transaction, this event handler will run
in the same transaction. And we will see
that if something fails here all the
transaction will be all beted. We have
the application modu probably it's
better to show this one. The
transactional event listener that is
another kind of listener. I'll do
comment it because it's interesting to
see. Yeah, that's basically a
transaction phase. The default is after
commit but we have also before commit.
We have after roll back and after
completion. That means that it runs even
if the transaction is rolled back or is
committed and yeah we have also other um
other interesting thing here but uh I
would like to show this one that is
basically a transaction
listener a default transaction listener
with a sync
run and transactional propagation
require new. It means that every time
you have an event and you use this
application module listener, you can at
least have at most have eventual
consistency. So it is not granted at all
that
uh this event will be sent as soon as
you have the event.
uh but you can handle it in the future.
So you will have at most uh eventual
consistency and the transactional event
listener can work with before commit and
after commit that it's basically a
synchronous version of the same
listener and yeah we can
try what happens
if course I I would like to have only a
listener
the structure is okay and I'll rerun my
application and switch here. So now I
can change the price for example for the
very first session. And here we see that
we received an event pre price changed
event with session and new price and
blah blah blah. We will use this events
later on. Uh but for now I would like to
show you something interesting.
If I here
throw except uh new runtime exception.
Okay. Sim simulating an error and I
rerun
it
and I reload this one and I change the
price again. Okay, I have this failed to
save. Okay, the interface is just for
for playing around. It's not really
good, but it's just to play to play
around. And here we see
that not
here. Okay, we have this runtime
exception with this simulating error and
the
price is not changed.
This is interesting because we are
running. Yeah, we are. This is
simplifies a little bit of things
because we have this event logger that
is defined in event logger application
and we are in another different module
that is session. We are run we are uh
yeah
um we are generating an event. So we
changed the price of the session. So we
generated this new event and in another
package we can leverage the spring
transactional model to roll back all the
transaction. This is really really handy
for simple cases. Of course, someone can
can argue and I I can agree about about
that that this is not really this is
make things really entangled but at some
stage you have to decide what what is
better for you and you can opt for
simplicity. So it's your choice to
decide which approach you can use
eventual consistencies consistency and
then you can use spring modulate
capabilities in order to retry to rep to
republish the event and I would like to
show this one and then I move
on. Okay.
Uh maybe I generate a trans an exception
here. Okay. And I run the the
application
again. All right. If I change the
price, this succeeded. Now why? because
we are but the runtime exception is
here. So what happened? We said it we
said that this this run after the
transaction commit we can see it again
because it is
interesting after the transaction commit
and it require a new
transaction. Okay. So this is something
that uh could you could use and I
suggest you to use to have uh eventual
consistency or for another use case that
I will show you afterwards. But let me
touch a little bit of things
and
yeah. Yeah. Let's go a little bit in the
future because we don't
have too much time. So let's see
what probably from here is better. So
I'll rerun the application
again. We can of course run also the
tests
but let's do like that. So we now have
an attendee. We can choose a an
attendee. We can, of course, search for
a session. As
before, I can add an item to my session.
I can't submit the order. Yeah,
maybe I should, but uh I can't submit
the order yet. I can try to add
another Yep. another item, the same
item. And this is a rule that we can see
in our in our aggregate route. We can't
add the same item to our cart. This is a
a domain rule that we invented. And now
we can change the
price. It is for discount. And we see
that here in the order summary because I
have an opened order. We have a price
updated and total
updated. You can you can say yeah you
know that you changed the price here.
You had a call back and you just updated
your user interface using JavaScript.
This is not the case. Of course, it
possib it's possible, but we use another
different approach. But let me show you
a little bit the order again. No, the
new order because it's a new class. It
is an aggregate. Uh I'll
close.
Thanks. Okay, it's an aggregate root
again. It's a final class. So, we can't
extend it. It extends aggregate root
with domain events. that is our class.
This we don't have we don't have uh
yeah spring dependencies or library
dependencies in our domain and in our
application. This is a choice you can
choose elsewhere. It depends on your
balance that you would like to take
about simplicity of what you implement
and about the
yeah a little bit more otherant way of
write code in
DDD but uh I'm not
against the one or the other it's your
choice and here we have
that method that will use uh afterward
that is check modify or throw to
complete the order to cancel the order.
So we have this order status that is
changed only only this is this is really
really important in the aggregate
route. We have also this add item and
the add item receive an item ID. We we
can see this this is a ubiquitous
language that you can use and what you
use in a bounded context. Oh, I didn't
show you the bounded context
thing. I'm really sorry for for this but
it is here. So here we are in the base
package net spring.io conference session
and we have this application module that
for
now yeah no this is uh this is uh right
the session module doesn't depends on
other module in our application this
empty brackets means that you you can't
basically use other model and this is
modulate we we didn't do anything this
is modulate that provide this module
structure
And this bounded context session. This
is what let our tests on DDD structure
working with the other. Of course,
because we we have this bounded context
that is from J
molecules and it means that in this
bounded this bounded context should
expose only thing that you would like to
expose and you have basically two way to
expose thing in uh in moderate.
they and I should have here exactly so
in the base package everything you put
in the base
package
session it's exposed to other
modules
otherwise other things are not exposed
at all but you can decide to expose
something to um to the other modules for
example we have the dom
domain event and here we have a package
info where we have defined a named
interface. That is the other way to say
hey the classes that you find here price
changed event from the session
aggregate they can be used by other and
we can see the mesh here in the order
because the order module depends on
session and session to uh
comma and
domain.vents. This is the way how we
can reference this is a named the
interface of the module session. So we
have this reference here in the order
package where we can use session and we
can use we can use session domain
events. If I remove this
one and this is something
I can show you. I'm
I'm Is it starting
or
okay?
Good. So module order depends on named
interface session domain
events and our application doesn't run
because we have this in the spring
conf
this verification usually usually people
make this verify in
tests it means that if
you uh run your test, you see that the
application
uh uh doesn't run. But this verification
prevent prevent that you run your
application when
uh you are for a mistake for example
going in in a in another environment. I
hope not in production with these kind
of things.
And yeah, yeah, you you should have
pipelines of course that test all your
code base,
but we
know could happen. And another thing
that we implemented here
is something that log all the module
structure. And I it's better to show you
here when it works
probably.
Okay. All right. So we have a registered
module attendee. We have a registered
module event logger. A module internal.
All right. There is no a simple a simple
way to exclude module right now. Uh so
to say this is not a module in the
modulate I I'm looking for it and I saw
that in the community
also. Yeah there is some
requests and we have also this order uh
no uh this session module session with
domain events and the module shirt. So
we can inspect also the structure here
but we can do something that is more
visual in
the in the future. Okay more or less 10
minutes. I would like to show you
something else just to a little bit
explain. Oh no I I discarded but it's
not a problem. I'll show you later on.
So what I would like to show you is that
when we have an uh yeah we have
also several domain events for the order
they are not exposed yet because they
are not used basically or even better
they are used they are used uh for a
thing that I I I'm going to show you
now.
So we have this price
changes listener that is a use case and
basically it receives all price changed
events from the session as you can see
here from the session domain events and
it retrieves the pending order having
item and for each It uses update price
that is a method inside the a method
inside the aggregate. As we said before
everything that changes the state of the
state of our aggregate should pass for
the aggregate route.
This is really really important because
and what what is the advantage that you
can uh go in the order and be sure that
everything that change this the internal
status of your order is here. It can't
happen outside. And
how for example here we have this order
items and we have get order
Mhm. Oh, we removed it. Never mind. So,
I can show it. If we create a gather
for Mhm.
Maybe get items next list copy of we are
returning a list of items that basically
are yeah if it
works a final class with with all with
all attribute final. So we can't change
the state the state of this item from
outside. So we can't just create another
item. can replace an item. But we can do
this only in the
aggregate.
And when we
get a list of this item, it is a a copy
that is not
mutable. This is really important
because if you know that if you return
an array list for example, someone from
outside can modify your internal state.
And this is something that
you don't
want. And yeah, but this is not what I
would like to show you. We have this
price change handler. And we are saving
all p yeah this p pending order. And
when we are modifying this if it's
modifiable of course because it can be
modified if it's it's pending then okay
then you have this replace all item that
matches the condition of course and then
you register this event order price
updated events. Yeah, probably if I
close this it's better. And if I updated
something then I register also the event
order total changed event and I have
this get total that is here and it's
public that basically recalculate every
time the total and what I send back is
the right value of course.
So we can see who used
this. Yes. So we have we have this event
notifier. this event notifier that is a
price changes notifier that implements
this application listener context close
because we have to close all the the SSS
emitters before the yeah before closing
our application as it stacks for a while
and we are using server side server side
event to
send changes that happen to our AR
order. So this is totally decoupled. And
here we can see that we have this
application module listener that is a
synchronous as we said before. Yeah, I
don't really care if the front end will
be updated. It's not interesting for me
that it should happen in a transaction.
If the front end receives the order,
it's okay. or or the the new item or the
new the new price for the item or the
new total. It's okay. Else if I refresh
or if I submit, of course, I use my
aggregate that has the correct
status. And yes, we can see the
controller
to where we have
this. Yeah.
order ID changes. So the our our uh
front end can register using SSA to this
SSC to this
um let me call it streaming of data and
when an event occurs then we publish
this event using server side event
channel that is opened and it is totally
implemented in in HTML. So we can use it
both in front end and in back end uh
with uh basically any framework because
it it's it's kind of standard and in the
front end of course we read these
changes and we know if we are
publishing
yes this one if we are publishing an
order updated event or if we are
publishing another
on. We have few minutes left and I would
like to show you. Um yeah, we
implemented also policy but I leave this
to you to see if you would like to see
it and I will go I will go to the last
comet where
we come to the end basically.
So what happens when you would like to
know how is your
structure? We created a
test
this
documentation. Okay.
And this test basically uses um modulate
to create the the structure of your
module and it write a a UML with or with
your module and I can run
it
and if it works it worked in the target
folder we will have spring modulate
docs
with
this. Just a
second.
Close all the
tabs. Okay, it doesn't work. Why?
Oh, probably for
this.
Okay, it worked.
So we can see this document that
basically
uh it's a simple version of our
documentation with the relation between
modules. So you can see that attendee
for example depends on shared modules
and you have some information some
interesting information here like
application layer find
attendees uh and also the
implementation. This is an interface.
Yeah, you can see we have this event
logger and so on,
but yeah, we have
to come back to Yep.
Okay, the presentation I'm going to
finish it
just a few takeaways. Do you remember
when I started saying that when we have
a micros service we have a lot of things
to orchestrate and we have to decide
who's the owner of what and when we uh
have a monolith basically you don't know
who is the owner owner or of something.
Well, in this way as we seen uh right
now we can decide who is the owner. It
is clear who is the owner and we have
some
boundaries. After we set the boundaries,
moving it from a modular monolith to
microservices is just something that we
can do when needed because we already
have boundaries and the boundaries will
decide the the modules
will eventually become uh
microser. Okay.
So this make make it very easy to evolve
a modular monolith into micros into a
microservices
set. We have ddd that help us to
recognize the boundaries because you
know we've seen that session is a
boundary and the attendees another
boundary. So we have something some some
rules that helps us to uh recognize and
decide how to uh create the modules and
set the
boundaries. We have a maintainable and
understandable architecture because the
test helps us to design it and put the
code in the right uh folder in the right
package.
Also we have some documentation not just
the documentation that a model generated
but the tests the tests that validate
the architecture tell us where to write
the right
code and we can describe it. we can code
it and test it and it just up to us to
decide what's the kind of architecture
that
uh works for us. We decided to use a
layered architecture and wrote some
tests to validate it but you can you can
decide to use for example an hexagonal
architecture you can write test to
validate that too. So just find out
which one works for you. Write some
tests because they will
validate your architecture now but your
architecture tomorrow and so
on. If you are curious curious to use
and find out all that things and
experiment this is the repository. So
you are
basically done and the time is up. It
should be okay public and everything.
Yeah. You let us know if it's not
public. It should be. It works. Okay.
Perfect. Thank you for the feedback.
Thank you. Thank you very much.